Freeman Hansford Hart Collection WLU.Coll.0129
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Freeman Hansford Hart Collection
1910-1965
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Hart, Freeman Hansford
WLU.Coll.0129
1 Linear Feet
Biographical / Historical
prof., b. Lexington, Va., Oct. 6, 1889; s. John Harvey and Susan (Gaylor) H.; A.B., Washington and Lee U., 1912, M.A., 1917; M.A., Harvard, 1922; PhD, Columbia, 1942; m. Jean Blanding Fraser, Junes 28, 1923; children- John Fraser, James Wilson, Abel McIver, David Edward, Jean Blanding. Prof. history Wash. Coll., Md., 1923-25; prof. history and economics Hampden-Sydney Coll., Va., 1915-40; prof. history extension div., U. of Va., 1928-41; prof. social sci. and humanities U. of Fla., Gainesville, since 1946, dir. Georgia Seagle Found. since 1947. Seved with A.E.F., World War I. Awarded Cross of Honor, United Daughters of Confederacy. Mem. Am. Hist. Assn., So. Hist. Soc., Fla. Hist. Soc., Va. Hist. Soc., Coll. Fraternities Secretary's Assn. (Exec. com. 1943-46), Pi Kappa Alpha (nat. historian 1930-49, nat. vice pres. 1936-38, nat. pres. 1938-40, exec. sec. 1940-46), Pi Beta Kappa, Tau Kappa Alpha, Sigma Upsilon, Kappa Phi Kappa. Independent. Presbetyrian. Club: Gainesville Rotary Author: Numerical Stength of Confederate Army (N.Y. Times Current History, Oct. 1926), History of Pi Kappa Alpha (1934, rev. 1949), The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution (U. of N.C. Press, 1943); author of articles in Dictionary of American Biography.
World War (1914-1918)
- Correspondence 1910-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Control (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1910-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains correspondence with Henry St. George Tucker regarding the maintenance of Lexington, Virginia's Col Alto estate, where Hart was residing prior to World War I. Also contains correspondane concerning WWI, including notices of military protocol. The U.S.S. Mongolia and 317th Infantry at Sea, and the medical detachment of which Hart was a part, are topics of interest.
    Virginia -- Lexington -- Col Alto; World War (1914-1918); United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 317th; U.S.S. Mongolia
  - Correspondence 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondances related to professional positions held, the publication of Hart's work, personal matters such as the illness of Hart's father, and military affairs.
  - Correspondence 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contains personal correspondence, military correspondence,and academic correspondence relating to Hart's published work, especially his doctoral dissertation, professional positions, and professional and speaking engagements. There is also a letter to a Dr. Fraser about presidential politics and prohibition in 1932, as well as one that seems to be about Hart's opinion about the possibility of WWII and U.S. involvement, though it is undated.
    Prohibition; World War (1939-1945)
  - Correspondence 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence related primarily to the publication of Hart's doctoral dissertation, 'The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution,' his gift of the work to friends, which are often personal letters, and reviews of this book. There is also correspondence concerning his speaking engagements, his review of a book by Foner,bibliographic information provided for Who's Who in America, a teaching position, a chapter Hart wrote for a book about several Presbetyrian chuches in the Valley of Virginia, his position in the Rockbridge Historical Society, and personal letters.
    Presbyterian Church; Rockbridge Historical Society
  - Correspondence 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence requesting historical information of Hart, professional inquiries, personal correspondence with fellow W&L alumni, other personal letters, and correspondence regarding an article about James Patton that Hart was co-authoring.
    Patton, James; Washington and Lee University
  - Correspondence 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence that is personal, related to Hart's collection of photographs for an article about James Patton Preston for The Commonwealth magazine, about other research related to this project, including information about Col. William Preston, James's father, and other professional and research correspondence. One letter of note is addressed to the editors of the Saturday Evening Post from B.R. Colson comparing liberalism and communism.
    Liberalism -- Philosophy; Communism; Patton, James; The Commonwealth Magazine; Preston, William; Saturday Evening Post
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 8, Box data_value_missing_ac3415315ab764338af0eb1f54a599ce)
    Items of note include a small travel brochure about New Orléans in French which includes a map and a professional dispute with the University of Florida. Other personal and professional correspondence from various years can be found here as well.
    Louisiana -- New Orleans; University of Florida
- Publications A-O (Box 2, Folder 9-16)
  - Book Reviews (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Reviews of Hart's work and reviews written by him. Includes reviews of Hart's The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution, Joseph H. Parks's General Kirby Smith, C.S.A., Philip S. Foner's Business and Slavery: The New York Merchants and the Irrepressible Conflict,Howard M. Wilson's The Tinkling Spring: Headwater of Freedom, Herbert Clarence Bradshaw's History of Prince Edward County, Virginia, E. Merton Coulter's Wormsloe: Two Centuries of a Georgia Family, and Robert L. Kincaid's The Wilderness Road.
  - Essays, Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Essays on topics including the relationship between citizenship and national defense, a denunciation of the legality of integration, the balence between faith and reason, whether the U.S. should enter the war (probably WWII), the American flag, a metaphorical lament of the wrongs done to the South, The Virginia Frontier on the Eve of the American Revolution, and an essay by Mr. B.R. Colson comparing liberalism and communism, addressed to the letters of the Saturday Evening Post, which he sent for Hart to read as discussed in an accompanying letter.
    Citizenship -- Philosophy; Social integration; Faith -- Philosophy; Reason -- Philosophy; World War (1939-1945); Liberalism; Communism; Southern states; Flags -- U.S. states
  - Civil War Material (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Material about Civil War commemorative events, a map of Stonewall Jackson's movements, a summary of the Battle of Antietam, a copy of A House Divided: The Civil War Letters of a Virginia Family, by W.G. Bean, a piece about Jefferson Davis, and an extract from 'The Congressional Globe' from January 21, 1861 about seccesion.
    Jackson, Thomas Jonathan (Stonewall); Davis, Jefferson
  - Lord Fairfax (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Material related to Hart's article 'Lord Fairfax and the Washingtons,' including parts of the article, drafts, and research materials.
  - Frontiersman Monument (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Photographs of the Frontiersman Monument.
    Frontiersman Monument; Photographs
  - John Lewis (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Two drafts of Hart's article 'John Lewis and his Sons: Frontier Builders.'
    Lewis, John
  - President James Monroe (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Hart's article 'James Monroe, Statesman, Extra-Ordinary' in several stages.
    Monroe, James
  - Battle of Olustee (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Materials including newspaper clippings, an article by Hart about the battle and correspondence concerning the editing process, an article by Hart titled 'Florida in the War between the States,' transcriptions of the 1860 census, a map of the battle, research notes, and information about a centennial reenactment.
    Florida
- Publications P-Z (Box 3, Folder 17-26)
  - Col. James Patton (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Graphic and written research materials, drafts of an essay about James Patton, correspondence about the writing process, research n notes,recommendations for editing, and a list of references to Patton.
    Patton, James
  - Col. William Preston (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Graphic and written research materials, research notes, a description of inserts, and drafts of the article Colonel William Preston- Frontier Builder.
    Preston, William
  - Speeches to the Daughters of the American Revolution (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Speeches to the Daughters of the American Revolution, including 'Seventy-five Years of Service for the Daughters of the American Revolution,' 'American History Month,' 'The Road to Communism,' 'One Nation under God,' and an anti-integration essay on the subject of the 'law of the land.'
    Communism; Social integration; Daughters of the American Revolution
  - Valley of Virginia- manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Manuscripts of The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution
    United States -- Shenandoah River Valley
  - Valley of Virginia- misc. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Material related to The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution, including book reviews, a piece about Zachariah Johnston, notes, a map, and publishing materials.
    United States -- Shenandoah River Valley; Johnston, Zechariah
  - Valley of Virginia- UNC Press (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Material relating to the publishing of The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution.
  - Virginia State History (Box 3, Folder 23, Box data_value_missing_1123615e31f8f38caf387e35cd66140d)
    Materials related to the history of Virginia including a booklet on the 1776 Virginia Convention, a booklet on Wichester and the Shenandoah Valley, a pamphlet for William Moseley Brown (a candidate for VA governor), a piece on 'The Madison-Jefferson Correspondence Concerning Religious Liberty, 1784-1789,' an article called 'The Potomac Route to the Western Waters,' an article called 'The Three Generals of the Valley,' a map, postcards, a 'Sketch of Virginia History for the French Veterans, Guests of the Nation,' a piece on Andrew Moore by a Miss Allen, and a thesis summary by Hart called 'Federalism in Virginia 1783-1788 with Special Reference to the Valley.'
    United States -- Shenandoah River Valley; Liberty -- Religious aspects; United States -- Potomac River; Virginia; Federal government; Brown, William Moseley; Madison, James; Jefferson, Thomas; Moore, Andrew
  - Dr. Thomas Walker (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Material related to Thomas Walker including a booklet called 'Dr. Thomas Walker: Father of Kentucky,' newspaper clippings, a piece c called 'Dr. Thomas Walker- Frontier Builder,' a scan of a primary source letter, and correspondence about writing the piece.
    Walker, Thomas, Dr.
  - George Washington (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Materials regarding George Washington including a postcard of his office, drafts of an article about him, and scans of primary source material.
    Washington, George
  - Alexander White (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Drafts of an article titled 'Alexander White- Frontier Builder.'
    White, Alexander
- Notes for Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution (Box 4)
  Eight tied groupings of Hart's research notes for his doctoral thesis, The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution.
- Notes for Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution (Box 5)
  Six tied groupings of Hart's research notes for his doctoral thesis, The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution.
- Notes for Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution (Box 6)
  Six tied groupings of research notes for Hart's doctoral thesis, The Valley of Virginia in the American Revolution.
- World War I Material (Box 7, Folder 27-34)
  World War (1914-1918)
  - Medical Detachment Ledger, 317th Infantry, United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 317th (Box 7, Folder 27)
    World War (1914-1918); Medicine
  - Maps (Box 7, Folder 28)
    World War (1914-1918); Maps
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Miscellaneous WWI material including uniform patches, a pamphlet for the Washington and Lee Victory Alumni Reunion, a small American Flag, a photograph of soldiers, a blank Liberty Loan Bond, a song sheet, inventory and personnel documents, personal items, and a graphic guide to identifying military insignia.
    Also included is an enveloped color brochure, "Flags of Our Country, National, State, Historic," published in 1962.
    World War (1914-1918); Flags -- U.S. states; Liberty bonds; World War (1914-1918); Military uniforms; Washington and Lee University
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 30)
    Roster and other beaureaucratic documents, a song lyric sheet, a description of meals for several days, and a publication titled Bulletin.
    World War (1914-1918); Printed ephemera
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7, Folder 31)
    Newspaper clippings related to WWI, including local Rockbridge County citizens' experiences, full pages from The New York Herald, the Stars and Stripes, The Bayonet, The News, and The Evening World.
  - Notebooks (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Several of Hart's notebooks from during WWI.
  - Pamphlets (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Pamphlets from during WWI, including a book of postcards of Loire Valley castles, a booklet on how to use a device used in the military, a pamphlet advertising WWI war bonds, a service song book, a booklet of prayers issued by the YMCA, a booklet in French titled Evangeline selon S. Marc: La Moisson Près de Bethanie, an Anglo-French phrase book, an active service French book, a booklet of appreciaton for WWI soldiers, a booklet of postcards called Les Américains en France, a pamphlet of useful French, a dual language booklet in French and English about the French soldier, a 'Pocket Treasury' of religious texts, and a booklet in French on the abbey of Fontevrault with photographs.
    World War (1914-1918); Castles; France -- Loire Valley; France
  - Postcards (Box 7, Folder 34)
    Postcards that are military issued and from different areas of France.
    World War (1914-1918); Postcards; France
- Publications (Printed Copies); misc.; biographical material (Box 8, Folder 35-51)
  - American Legion and Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity Materials (Box 8, Folder 35)
    Papers and newspaper clippings related to the history of the Pi Kappa Alpha fraternity and Hart's role as American Leigion historian
    Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity; American Legion
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 8, Folder 36)
    Newspaper clippings primarily related to Hart and his work
  - Biographical Material (Box 8, Folder 37)
    Biographical information including a list of achievements from Who's Who in America, a summary from the Literary Map - Biographical Guide of Virginia authors, a W&L yearbook entry about Hart, a list of Hart's publications, and a document resembling a resume
  - W&L Memorabilia (Box 8, Folder 38)
    Contains materials regarding the bicentennial celebration at W&L, a reunion book for the class of 1912, and a Ring Tum Phi article from WWI about students including Hart leaving for war
    World War (1914-1918); Ring-Tum Phi; Washington and Lee University
  - Miniature Hamlet (Box 8, Folder 39)
    Miniature Hamlet which Hart carried with him during WWI
    World War (1914-1918); Hamlet (Legendary character); Shakespeare, William
  - Current History, October, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    see page 91 for article by Hart
    Current History
  - Tyler's Quarterly Historical, January, 1927 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    see page 155 for mention of Hart's Current History article
    Tyler's Quarterly Historical
  - Indiana Magazine of History, March, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    see page 83 for book review by Hart
    Indiana Magazine of History
  - The Commonwealth, July, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    see page 9 for article by Hart
    The Commonwealth Magazine
  - The Commonwealth, April, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    see page 13 for article by Hart
  - The Commonwealth, December, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    see page 50 for article by Hart
  - The Commonwealth, September, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - The Commonwealth, October, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    see page 17 for article by Hart
  - The Commonwealth, December, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    see page 33 for article by Hart
  - The Commonwealth, March, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    see page 11 for article by Hart
  - The Commonwealth, July, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - The Florida Times Union Sunday Magazine, April 4, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    see page 16 for article by Hart
    The Florida Times Union Sunday Magazine